Guide to the Helen E. Hokinson Cartoons for The New Yorker
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Helen E. Hokinson Cartoons for The New Yorker
1926-1949
YCAL MSS 1084
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
25.42
15 boxes
The collection consists of more than 340 cartoons, cover drawings, and concept sketches in ink, pencil, watercolor, crayon, and charcoal on paper that were created for The New Yorker magazine by Helen E. Hokinson.
Hokinson, Helen E. (Helen Elna), 1893-1949
Barlow, Perry, 1892-1977
Geraghty, James M., 1905-1983
Parker, James Reid, 1909-1984
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Reid Parker, 1980.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series by the number of the portfolio in which they were received. Within each series the drawings are arranged in order of a numbered inventory that accompanied the collection.
Helen E. Hokinson (1893-1949)
Helen Elna Hokinson was born on June 29, 1893, in Mendota, Illinois, the daughter of Mary Wilcox Hokinson and Adolph Hokinson, a farm machinery salesman. After graduating from Mendota High School in 1913, she attended the Academy of Fine Arts in Chicago, and drew fashion illustrations for local department stores. Moving to New York in 1920, she studied at the New York School of Fine and Applied Art (later the Parsons School of Design) and worked as an illustrator for several of the city's fine department stores including Lord & Taylor and B. Altman and Company. Equally interested in cartooning, Hokinson submitted a drawing to The New Yorker within months of the magazine's founding in 1925, and was hired to make sketches at cultural events in the city such as art exhibitions or dance and music recitals. Thereafter the magazine published nearly 1,800 of her cartoons and vignettes within its covers, and sixty-eight of her watercolor drawings on its covers, until just after her death in 1949.
Helen Hokinson became one of the best-known of The New Yorker cartoonists, in company with Charles Addams, Peter Arno, Whitney Darrow Jr, George Price, and James Thurber. Working from her apartment in New York's Gramercy Park neighborhood or her cottage in Silvermine, Connecticut, she created her own genre of civic-minded "Hokinson women," described by Richard Merkin in a short profile of the artist published in The New Yorker in 1994: "Her dowagers and clubwomen were generally edging up on their fifties, were overweight (but intent on doing something about it), and were addicted to chapeaus that somehow always looked both chic and wrong. They were women of cheerful mien, earnest in their cultural and horticultural pursuits, and inclined toward the ingenuous. It was easy to laugh at them, but something about them—perhaps their energy, perhaps their tiny feet—made you laugh gently and with affection." Hokinson set her subjects in women's club meetings, community theatricals, country fairs, and flower and pet shows as well as at the opera, art museums, and, naturally, a wide variety of retail shops. Many of her early cartoons were published without captions, but eventually she, and most of the magazine's other cartoonists, began to use captions assigned by editors or staff writers, some of whom would first suggest captions for which Hokinson would then fashion an image.
In 1931 James Reid Parker, who wrote humorous pieces and light sketches for The New Yorker, met Helen Hokinson and the two became a professional team with Parker supplying captions for Hokinson's drawings. They met once a week, on Fridays, to exchange and develop ideas, and communicated daily by postcard if either was traveling. Their arrangement continued until Hokinson's death in an airplane crash on November 1, 1949; Parker served as the executor of her estate.
The editors wrote an appreciative farewell to Helen Hokinson in their November 12, 1949, issue: "Miss Hokinson's first drawing appeared in The New Yorker on July 4, 1925. The magazine was less than five months old then, and it was singularly fortunate in finding, at its difficult beginning, an artist of such rare and gentle distinction. In the years since then, her pictures have appeared in these pages almost every week, and the ladies she drew have become perhaps the most widely known and certainly the most affectionately cherished of any characters we have introduced to our readers. If satire is defined as an exposure of anyone's weakness, she was not a satirist at all, or even a humorist, if there is any implication of harshness in that. Her work was the product of loving observation and a boundless delight in all absurdity, none more than that she found in herself, and the pleasure she gave other people was really a reflection of her own."
Helen Hokinson's cartoons were published in three collections during her lifetime, So You're Going to Buy a Book! (Minton, Balch & Co., 1931), My Best Girls (New York: E. P. Dutton, 1941), and When Were You Built? (New York: E. P. Dutton & Co., 1948), and three after her death: The Ladies, God Bless 'em (New York: E. P. Dutton & Co., 1950), There are Ladies Present (New York: E. P. Dutton & Co., 1952), and The Hokinson Festival (New York: E. P. Dutton & Co. 1956).
Related Materials
James Reid Paper Papers (YCAL MSS 371), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of more than 340 cartoons, cover drawings, and concept sketches in ink, pencil, watercolor, crayon, and charcoal on paper that were created for The New Yorker magazine by Helen E. Hokinson. Many were signed by the artist and few are dated except by stamps and notes applied by the magazine's production staff. The drawings that are dated range from 1926 to 1949, but in general the works are chiefly from the 1930s and 1940s. There are more than thirty drawings or sketches meant for covers (easily recognizable by the distinctive color bar running along the left edge of the image) as well as several multi-panel cartoons that read like storyboards (for example, Series VI, drawing 64: So You're Going to Have Your Picture Taken!).
The drawings primarily feature situations in which Hokinson's iconic matrons interact with their friends, cultural colleagues, children, pets, sales clerks, and their stalwart household staff members (two examples in Series VII: in drawing 78, a matron stepping off a train tells her driver, "I have two sheep in the baggage car, Gordon, they're for the lawn." and in drawing 76, a matron alone with her housekeeper says, "Alice, go look at my engagement pad and tell me what I'm doing."). The city and suburban scenarios are those Hokinson knew well: department stores, women's clubs, box offices, amateur theater stages, pet shows, cocktail parties, and anywhere that American tourists would be seen abroad. Much of her humor is visual and not always obvious from a caption (Series VII, drawing 10, "Where are the guns, please?" features a woman and small boy in the stuffed animal section of a toy store; Series VI, drawing 63, "Do you all give up?" depicts a game of charades in which the matron is on the floor posed as a sphinx) and many of the references, such as those to cosmetics magnate Richard Hudnut, theater star Maurice Evans, United States Vice President Henry A. Wallace, and to Briarcliff Junior College, are no longer relatable in the twenty-first century. However, the gentle humor that Hokinson applied to her ladies and their circumstances both mirrors and transcends its time, and some of the cartoons—in particular the matron whispering to a Paris bookstall attendant in French about James Joyce's banned Ulysses (Series VII, drawing 8, published May 22, 1930) or walking out on a performance of Igor Stravinsky's The Rite of Spring (remarking "Mr. Damrosch will hear of this." in Series VII, drawing 26), or the two matrons in an art gallery quizzically circling Constantin Brancusi's Bird in Space (Series VII, drawing 173, published February 6, 1926) or pausing to query a Southwest pueblo resident about the legendary Mabel Dodge Luhan (Series IV, drawing 12, published July 9, 1938)—present cultural markers still of interest to readers many decades afterward.
Drawings that carry on their versos the magazine's copyright stamp, serial numbers in blue or black crayon, and directions to the printer regarding image size and placement, indicate that they had been published. Those without may be rejected ideas or weren't submitted for consideration, and in six cases the drawings are accompanied by notes (usually rejection notes) from James M. Geraghty (1905-1983), art editor at The New Yorker from 1939 to 1973; one mentions Harold Ross (1892-1951), the magazine's founder and editor-in-chief. However, although unmarked, some of the drawings may have appeared in the magazine's category of "covering art"—groups or sequences of images which appeared on a page or two, usually with a one- or two-word caption—or as vignettes in the "Goings On" or "Talk of the Town" sections of the magazine. In two cases the collection holds drawings that are in both cartoon and cover formats: the three matrons touring Mexico in Series VI, drawing 46, appear in a cover design in Series VII, drawing 68, and the tennis club group in Series VII, drawing 104, is also in a cover sketch in Series VII, drawing 18.
In addition to the cartoons there are three watercolor views of rural France in Series III (drawings 39-41) taken when Hokinson visited there in the late 1920s, and four unidentified watercolor views in Series VII (drawings 73, 79, 129, and 143) as well as two printed pieces: a progressive proof of a Hokinson cover on the June 22, 1946, issue (Series VII, number 17) and in the same series, number 69 is a detached Hokinson cover from January 5, 1946. Also present is a 1931 cartoon by Perry Barlow (1892-1977), her colleague at The New Yorker (Series VI, drawing 78).
The drawings in this collection were among a larger group left as a bequest by Helen Hokinson to her friend Helen Mobert (1896-1979). Before they were transferred to Mobert, James Reid Parker (1909-1984), Hokinson's executor and primary caption writer, added captions on the drawings which had none. In the subsequent thirty years, Mobert sold most of the drawings she had inherited, and at her death the residue passed to Parker. Mobert had written new captions on many of the drawings; Parker erased those captions and rewrote the originals, either from memory when the caption was his own or from published sources when the drawing was executed before he began collaborating with Hokinson. The captions in the box and folder list below were transcribed as they appear on the drawings. Those with quotation marks indicate that a character in the cartoon is speaking. Those without quotes are simply titles applied by Hokinson or Parker, and [descriptions in brackets] are for drawings with no caption or title present.
New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); American wit and humor, Pictorial; Artists -- United States; Cartoonists -- United States; Cartoons (humorous images) -- United States -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Illustrations (layout features) -- United States -- 20th Century; Watercolors (paintings) -- United States -- 19th century; Artists -- United States -- 20th Century; Cartoonists -- United States -- 20th Century; Barlow, Perry, 1892-1977; Geraghty, James M., 1905-1983; Hokinson, Helen E. (Helen Elna), 1893-1949; Parker, James Reid, 1909-1984
- Portfolio 1, Series I
  - 1. "I always mistrust the ones that win a lot of prizes." (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 1/4 x 13 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above another version: "I always mistrust them when they get a lot of prizes.", which is written in pencil over a previously erased caption with different wording. A6070 written in blue crayon on verso, portion of second 0 cut away.
  - 2. "I hope I haven't alarmed you about Dartmouth." (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 3/4 x 15 3/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over a previously erased caption with different wording. A71096 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 3. "Suppose I tell you the kind of life I lead, and you suggest something." (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 12 1/4 x 14 3/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over a previously erased caption with different wording. A6239 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 4. "It's the same lecture, but for twenty dollars more he wears a leopard skin.", 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 11 3/4 x 14 3/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over a previously erased caption with different wording. A8906 written in pencil on verso, portion of the 6 cut away. Date 1/16/32 written in pencil on verso.
  - 5. "Surely you must have something a young ensign might use on a destroyer." (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 x 11 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over a previously erased caption with different wording. A513 written in blue crayon on verso; evidence of cropping suggests that this number had a fourth digit subsequently cut away.
  - 6. "Well, I'm saving my lira for an antipasto binge on a rainy day." (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 16 x 13 1/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. AA6795 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 7. "It happened like this. One day Miss Arden was looking at a beautiful sunset..." (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 11 x 8 3/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above a portion of the same caption (written in another hand), the remainder cut away. AS written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 8. "Do you think it's serious enough for a party of the president of Princeton?" (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 x 15 3/4". Caption written in pencil over previously erased caption with same wording. A1477 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 9. "I've been driving for a whole year, and you're the first person who hasn't got out of my way." (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil with onlay correction pasted to upper portion of drawing, 14 x 17 3/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over a previously erased caption with same wording. A1230 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 10. "What I didn't learn about Charles the Second in the book they sent last month!" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 x 14 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over a previously erased caption. A6997 written in blue crayon on verso, portion of the 7 cut away.
  - 11. "My husband is going to shoot me, but I don't care.", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 1/2 x 12 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above a previously erased caption with different wording. AA5511 written in crayon on verso. Jun 22 1940 stamped on Kraft paper cover sheet.
  - 12. "But if you married a man named Kimball your first year out of college, what on earth did you do with Albert Fowler?" (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 17 x 13 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above a previously erased caption with different wording. A8501 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 13. "Never mind, Mrs. Jones. We'll take the will for the deed.", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 18 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption with same wording. Oct 17 1934 stamped on verso. AA1457 written in blue crayon on verso.
- Portfolio 2, Series II
  - 1. The thrill of buying your first car (Box 2, Folder 14)
    A sequence of six panel drawings, black ink and gray wash over pencil, each drawing 3 1/2 x 5", together mounted on a 14 3/4 x 12" sheet; captions written in pencil on the mounting sheet below each drawing and on the verso of the mounting sheet in variant wordings.
  - 2. Some day, in an unexpected place, you will likely meet an Old Friend. says the O. F. "I'm just over in Westchester—next-door neighbors—drop in any time!" (Box 2, Folder 15)
    A sequence of nine panel drawings, black ink and gray wash over pencil, each drawing 5 x 5 1/2", together mounted on a 16 x 18" sheet backed with cardboard. Captions written in black ink at foot of each drawing; the first and fourth captions with correction onlays.
  - 3. Very likely, one day, an otherwise intelligent friend will announce, "My dear, I've been to the most marvelous astrologist!" (Box 2, Folder 16)
    A sequence of nine panel drawings, black ink and gray wash over pencil, each drawing 4 x 5", mounted in rows of three on 14 1/2 x 6" sheets. Captions typewritten on the mounting sheet below each drawing.
  - 4. Very likely a gentleman will say to you some evening—"I wonder how you'd look with you hair long." (Box 2, Folder 17)
    A sequence of six panel drawings, black ink and gray wash over pencil, the drawings 4 1/2 x 5" and 4 1/2 x 6", together mounted on a 16 1/2 x 11 1/4" sheet. Captions written in black ink at foot of each drawing.
  - 5. "Perhaps I should get a size larger this time. They seem to shrink after I get them." (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 1/2 x 14 1/4". Caption written in pencil over two previously erased captions with different wording. A8997 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 6. So you're going to play bridge! (Box 11, Folder 240)
    A sequence of eight panel drawings, black ink and gray wash over pencil, the drawings, 5 x 5" and 5 x 6", numbers 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 8 in panels of two, 5 and 6 separate, together mounted on a 20 x 12" sheet. Title written in red crayon on upper left margin of drawing number 2; captions written in black ink at foot of each drawing.
  - 7. So you're going to hire a secretary! (Box 11, Folder 241)
    A sequence of nine panel drawings, black ink and gray wash over pencil, the drawings 5 1/2 x 6"; numbers 5, 6, 8, 9 in a panel of four, numbers 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 are separate, together mounted on an 18 x 19" sheet. Title written in red crayon on panel above drawing number 2; captions written in black ink at foot of each drawing.
  - 8. [Two children and their chauffeur at the Automat.], 1938 (Box 11, Folder 242)
    Black ink and watercolor, 11 3/8 x 8 3/4" in an exhibition mat. Drawing for cover published February 26, 1938.
  - 9. [Street scene in India. American family—husband, wife, daughter, and family dog on leash, and an Indian guide—encounter a snake charmer.], 1931 (Box 11, Folder 243)
    Black ink and watercolor, 11 3/8 x 8 3/4"; label on lower right corner of exhibition mat: "Helen Hokinson Issue of August 22, 1931." Drawing for cover published on August 22, 1931.
- Portfolio 3, Series III
  - 1. [Woman talking to a man, both seated on deck chairs on an ocean liner] (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 x 15 3/4". Caption erased but remains partially visible. AA8041 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 2. "Where are the hats for better women?" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Black ink and gray wash. over pencil, 17 1/2 x 13 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over a previously erased caption with different wording. A7902 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 3. "I'd never let a doll of mine wear a dress like that." (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 x 14 1/2"; caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased caption. AA5582 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 4. Carnegie Hall—Saturday morning. "Hurry up! The band's already started." (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 12 x 16 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased captions. AA3065 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 5. "By the way, did the Queen ever send Mrs. Roosevelt a bread-and-butter letter?" (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 1/2 x 17 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased captions with variant wording. AA9633 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 6. "Don't go, everybody! There are lots more commentators to come." (Box 11, Folder 244)
    pencil sketch, 14 x 21 3/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing, unsigned. Upper and lower left corners missing, 1 x 5 1/2" piece cut from sheet below caption, 4" tear in sheet into drawing up from middle of bottom edge, small portion missing from right edge of sheet.
  - 7. "Does your husband want you to look dark and mysterious?" (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 1/2 x 13 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over a previously erased caption with same wording and above a previously erased caption with variant wording.
  - 8. The painters are due to come early Monday morning...SO... (Box 2, Folder 25)
    A sequence of four panel drawings, black ink and gray wash over pencil, the drawings 4 1/2 x 5" and 5 x 5 1/2" are in two panels of 4 1/ 2 x 12" and 6 x 12" with a title panel 2 1/4 x 12". Title written in pencil on panel at head of drawings; captions written in black ink at foot of each drawing.
  - 9. "I like and respect Dr. Kimball, but I wish he looked more romantic in the pulpit." (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 15 3/4 x 15". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing over previously erased captions with variant wording.
  - 10. "If this were Venice, we could have haggled over the price." (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 14 1/4 x 16 1/2". Correction onlay over left half and upper third of drawing. Caption written in pencil at foot of correction onlay. A7945 written in blue crayon on verso, portion of A cut away.
  - 11. So you want a little house in the country! (Box 2, Folder 28)
    A sequence of nine panel drawings, black ink and gray wash over pencil, each drawing 5 x 5", drawings 1, 2, 5, 7, 8 on one panel 17 x 11 1/2", drawings 3 & 6 on one panel 11 1/2 x 6 1/2", drawings 4 and 9 separate, together mounted on an 18 x 18 1/2" sheet. Title written in black ink at head of drawings; captions written in black ink at foot of each drawing.
- Portfolio 4, Series IV
  - 1. "Perhaps I ought to explain we're beginning to think about boys." (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 13 x 12 1/2". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above a previously erased caption—with same wording. AA8218 written in blue crayon on verso.
  - 2. Session at the library. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 11 3/4 x 9 3/4". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing. A4370 written in black crayon on verso.
  - 3. [Man in tails playing grand piano] (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Black ink over pencil, 12 1/4 x 10 1/4" mounted on a 14 3/4 x 11 1/4" sheet; no caption.
  - 4. Dancing class—a disgusted advanced pupil draws a beginner. (Box 10, Folder 170)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 7 1/4 x 5 1/4". Caption written in pencil at head of drawing. 138 written in black crayon on verso.
  - 5. "At last I've found a clerk who takes an interest in my feet!", 1931 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 11 x 15". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above a previously erased caption with same wording. A8449 written in blue crayon on verso. Date 9/12/31 written in pencil on verso; published on p. 64 of the September 12, 1931, issue.
  - 6. "You can't expect to find a perfect man." (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Black ink and gray wash over pencil, 11 x 11". Caption written in pencil at foot of drawing above a previously erased caption with same wording.
  - 7. "I wonder if wild rice would be a thrill for Colonel Parker?" (Box 3, Folder 34)